<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A copy of the decree wherein two bookes of Roger Widdrington an English Cathotholick [sic] are condemned, and the author commanded to purge himselfe: and a copy of the purgation which the same Roger Widdrington sent to his Holinesse Pope Paul the fift. Translated out of Latine into English by the author, whereunto he hath also adioined an admonition to the reader concerning the Reply of T.F. &amp;c. and the condemnation of Fa: Suarez booke by a decree of the Parliament of Paris.</title>
            <title>Exemplar decreti. English</title>
            <author>Preston, Thomas, 1563-1640.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1614</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 81 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 34 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15317</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25606</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119081</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854288</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854288</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19699</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A15317)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19699)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1536:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A copy of the decree wherein two bookes of Roger Widdrington an English Cathotholick [sic] are condemned, and the author commanded to purge himselfe: and a copy of the purgation which the same Roger Widdrington sent to his Holinesse Pope Paul the fift. Translated out of Latine into English by the author, whereunto he hath also adioined an admonition to the reader concerning the Reply of T.F. &amp;c. and the condemnation of Fa: Suarez booke by a decree of the Parliament of Paris.</title>
                  <title>Exemplar decreti. English</title>
                  <author>Preston, Thomas, 1563-1640.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>67, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Permissu superiorum. 1614.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"To the reader" signed: Roger Widdrington (pseudonym of Thomas Preston).</note>
                  <note>A translation of: Preston, Thomas.  Exemplar decreti.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication from STC.</note>
                  <note>"A copy of Roger Widdringtons purgation" has caption title.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Fitzherbert, Thomas, 1552-1640. --  Reply of T.F. --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Suárez, Francisco, 1548-1617. --  Defensio fidei --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church. --  Congregatio Indicis --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church and statex --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Oath of allegiance, 1606 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19699:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19699:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A COPY OF THE DECREE: WHEREIN TWO BOOKES OF ROGER WIDDRINGTON an Engliſh Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick are condemned, and the Author commanded to purge himſelfe: AND A Copy of the Purgation which the ſame ROGER WIDDRINGTON ſent to <hi>his Holineſſe Pope Paul</hi> the fift.</p>
            <p>Tranſlated out of Latine into Engliſh by the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor,</hi> whereunto he hath alſo adioined an <hi>Admonition</hi> to the Reader concerning the <hi>Reply</hi> of <hi>T. F.</hi> &amp;c. and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation of <hi>Fa: Suarez</hi> booke by a Decree of the Parliament of Paris.</p>
            <q>He that iuſtifieth the wicked, and he that condemneth the iuſt, both are abhominable before God.
<bibl>
                  <hi>Prou. 17.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <figure>
               <head>IHS</head>
            </figure>
            <p>Permiſſu Superiorum. 1614.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:19699:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19699:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here came forth ſome few monethes ſince <hi>(Chriſtian Reader)</hi> out of the ſupreme tribunall of the holy Inquiſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, a Decree printed at Rome by the Printer of the Apoſtolicall Chamber, &amp; to be publiſhed throughout the whol Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian world, wherein two Bookes which I wrote with a ſimple, and ſincere intention, are condemned, and the Author commanded to purge himſelfe forthwith. I haue obeyed their command, and made forthwith my purgati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and haue done as much as lyeth in me, to ſend it forthwith to <hi>his Holineſſe.</hi> But becauſe that Decree is printed, and publiſhed in euery place, and the purgation which <hi>I</hi> haue ſent is only in written hand, leſt Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes ſhould perchance imagine, that <hi>I</hi> haue not been carefull to fulfill <hi>his Holineſſe</hi> command for purging my ſelfe, <hi>I</hi> thought it neceſſarie to Print alſo, and publiſh that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuſcript purgation which <hi>I</hi> haue ſent, which otherwiſe without doubt would come into few mens hands, that ſo the whole world may ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely
<pb facs="tcp:19699:3"/>
iudge as well of my purgation, as of that condemnation of my bookes, and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>I</hi> am to be accounted a Catholike and a child of the Church, or an Heretike, and an enemie thereof, as ſome men very irreligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, yet vnder pretext forſooth of religion, are not afraid. (<hi>I</hi> pray God forgiue them) to giue forth ſpeeches of me.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thy brother and ſeruant in Ieſus Chriſt, ROGER WIDDRINGTON.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="decree">
            <pb facs="tcp:19699:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A Copy of the Decree. A DECREE</hi> To bee publiſhed euery where, made by the Sacred Congregation of the moſt Honourable Cardinals of the holy Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Church, ſpecially deputed by our moſt Holy Lord Pope <hi>Paule</hi> the fifth, and the holy Apoſtolike Sea, for the examination of bookes, and their permiſſion, prohibition, purgation, and impreſſion throughout the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall common-wealth.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Sacred Congregation of the moſt Honorable Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals of the holy Romane Church, deputed for the examination of Bookes, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſeene a Booke falſly intituled, <hi>An Apologie of Cardinall</hi> Bellarmine <hi>for the right of Princes, againſt his owne reaſons for the Popes authority to depoſe Secular Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, in order to ſpirituall good, written by</hi> Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger Widdrington, <hi>an Engliſh Catholike,
<pb facs="tcp:19699:4"/>
in the yeare of our Lord</hi> 1611. And ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Book of the ſame Authour, intituled, <hi>A Theologicall Diſputation concerning the Oath of Allegiance, dedicated to the moſt Holy Father</hi> Pope Paule <hi>the fifth, printed at</hi> Albionopolis, <hi>in the yeare of our Lord</hi> 1613. hath iudged both the Bookes worthy to bee condemned, and prohibited, and by the commaundement of our moſt Holie Lord <hi>Pope Paul</hi> the fifth, doth by this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Decree, vtterly condemne, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibite them in what language ſoeuer they are printed, or to be printed: and except the <hi>Author</hi> of them, who profeſſeth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to be a Catholike, do purge (or cleere) himſelfe forthwith, hee is to vnderſtand, that he ſhall bee throughly puniſhed with Cenſures, and other Eccleſiaſticall puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. Furthermore, it commandeth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the penalties contained in the holy Councell of <hi>Trent,</hi> and in the Index of forbidden Bookes, that none, of what de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, or condition ſoeuer, be ſo bold from henceforth to print the foreſaid bookes, or cauſe them to be printed, or keepe them with him in any ſort, or reade them. Alſo it commandeth vnder the ſame penalties that whoſoeuer haue them now, or ſhal
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:19699:4"/>
haue them hereafter, he ſhall preſently vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the knowledge of this preſent Decree, exhibite them to the Ordinaries of the places (where he is) or the Inquiſitours. In teſtimony whereof this preſent Decree was ſigned, and ſealed with the hand, and ſeale of the moſt Honorable, and moſt Reuerend Lord, the Lord Cardinall of S. <hi>Caecilia</hi> Byſhop of <hi>Alba,</hi> the 10. of March 1614.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>P. Byſhop of Alba,</hi> Card. of S. Caecilia. The place ❀ for the Seale.</signed>
               <hi>Regiſt. fol.</hi> 50.
<signed>
                  <hi>Fr. Thomas Pallauicinus</hi> of the Order of Preachers, <hi>Secretarie.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>
                  <hi>Printed in Rome by the Printer of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolicall Chamber.</hi> 1614.</p>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <div type="admonition_to_the_reader">
            <head>
               <hi>An Admonition to the Reader,</hi> concerning the Reply of T. F. &amp;c.</head>
            <p n="1">1 THis Decree of the Sacred Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, as it is thus tranſlated into Engliſh, I haue <hi>(Courteous Reader)</hi> taken out of <hi>M. T. F.</hi> lately publiſhed, whoſe
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:19699:5"/>
vnſound, and inſufficient handling this Controuerſie, but yet ſomewhat cunning, and colourable, and therefore eaſie to blinde the eyes of the ſimple, I will, God willing, ere it be long moſt clearely, but modeſtly diſcouer. In the meane time, thou maieſt very plainely perceiue the weakneſſe of his Diſcourſe (to omit his intemperate and vncharitable bitterneſſe) if thou doſt but conſider the true ſtate of the Controuerſie, which is betwixt vs, and that all his Replies muſt be either euident demonſtrations, or inuincible au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorities, to which no probable anſwer can be giuen, otherwiſe he onely beateth about the buſh, and will neuer prooue that which he pretended to conuince; and wilt alſo be pleaſed but ſleightly to reade ouer the <hi>Appendix</hi> to my Theologicall Diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, wherein I fully anſwered all the arguments, which <hi>Fa: Suarez</hi> bringeth to demonſtrate the doctrine for the Popes power to depoſe Princes to be a point of faith; which Doctrine as this Authour confeſſeth, is the maine queſtion between him and me: and therefore for the better confirmation of his Reply, hee nakedly vrgeth all <hi>Fa: Suarez</hi> arguments (but
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:19699:5"/>
concealing his name) which I in that Appendix haue already fully ſatisfied.</p>
            <p n="2">2 For <hi>firſt,</hi> I plainely declared the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of that diſtinction, which I alledged betwixt the Popes power to command temporals, and to puniſh temporally by way of coërtion, which diſtinction ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth greatly to trouble this Author, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he perceiueth, that it ſatisfieth the chiefeſt Arguments, which are vſually brought from the authoritie of many Canons, and from the nature and effects of Excommunication, to prooue, that the Pope hath power, not onely by the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiledges of Princes, but alſo by Chriſt his inſtitution, and by conſequence of his Paſtorall office, to diſpoſe of temporals, and to inflict temporall puniſhments by way of coërcion.</p>
            <p n="3">3 <hi>Secondly,</hi> I ſhewed, that <hi>Marſilius</hi> of <hi>Padua,</hi> whom with other enemies of the Church, <hi>Suarez</hi> affirmeth to haue firſt impugned this Doctrine of depoſing tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall Princes by the Popes ſpirituall au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, was not by Catholike writers of former times accounted an heretick, for that he did impugne this Doctrine, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do thoſe Authours, who relate <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilius</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:19699:6"/>
his errours, as <hi>Caſtro, Prateolus, D. Sanders,</hi> and others, note this for one, that the Pope hath not power to depoſe Princes; which is an euident ſigne, that before this our miſerable age, that Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine for the Popes power to depoſe Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, was not accounted by Catholickes to be a point of faith.</p>
            <p n="4">4 <hi>Thirdly,</hi> that from the time of <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorie</hi> the ſeuenth, who was the firſt Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour, that cleerely taught this Doctrine, (but after he had firſt put it in practiſe) and was the firſt Pope, that, <hi>contrarie to the cuſtome of his Anceſtors</hi> (ſaith <hi>Onuphrius) depoſed the Roman Emperour</hi> (for which cauſe he had much adoe to cleere himſelf euen with his own friends, as appeareth by the Letter, which <hi>Hermannus Biſhop of Mentz,</hi> his deare friend, and follower in all ſuch his proceedings, wrote vnto him, deſiring to be ſatisfied herein, and was by <hi>Sigebert,</hi> who in thoſe dayes was greatly eſteemed by the wiſeſt for his ſingular vertue, and learning, although <hi>Cardinal Baronius,</hi> and <hi>Cardinall Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine</hi> doe without ſufficient ground call him a Sciſmatick, at that time impeached
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:19699:6"/>
               <hi>of noueltie,</hi> not to ſay, <hi>of hereſie,</hi> for ſo bee <hi>Sigeberts</hi> words) it hath been conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually euen to theſe our daies contradict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Catholike Authors, as appeareth by <hi>Ioannes Trithemius,</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Jn Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nico Mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterii Hir. ſaug. ad an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num <hi>1106.</hi>
               </note> and <hi>Iacobus Almai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">In lib. a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> dominio na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turali &amp;c. inprobatione concluſ 2 ae.</note> there related, but eſpecially by <hi>the Kingdome of France,</hi> as witneſſeth <hi>Petrus Pithaeus,</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">In codice libertatum Eccleſ. Galli canae.</note> a man greatly commended by <hi>Fa: Poſſeuine</hi> the Ieſuit, for his ſingular learning and knowledge in Antiquities,<note n="d" place="margin">In Appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratu verbo Petrus Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thaeus.</note> and it is ſufficiently confirmed by the late proceeding <hi>at Paris</hi> againſt the bookes of <hi>Card: Bellarmine, Becanus Schulckenius,</hi> and now laſtly of <hi>Suarez,</hi> whoſe booke was for this Doctrine by a ſolemne Decree of the Parliament of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris, and Printed by the Kings Printer, and with the Kings priuiledge condemned, and reprochfully burned the 27. of Iune paſt by the hangman, before the great Staires of the Pallace, and foure of the chiefeſt Ieſuites of France therein named, were enioyned vnder paine of treaſon in their Sermons to exhort the people to the contrarie Doctrine: And doubtleſſe this Authour, who in all points followeth theſe former mens ſteps, if his booke had beene printed in Latine, would haue
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:19699:7"/>
quickly perceiued by the fruits of his own labours, whether in France there be any Catholikes, who doe impugne this Doctrine of depoſing Princes by the Popes authoritie, or no: And yet this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour would cunningly perſwade the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pler ſort of Catholikes, therby to perplexe their conſciences, that I onely am the man, who doe impugne this temporall authoritie of the Pope to depoſe Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; whereas hee cannot be ignorant, that beſides mee, many others of our nation, as both the <hi>Barclaies,</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Blackwell,</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Warmington,</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Barret,</hi> thoſe thirteene <hi>Reuerend Prieſts,</hi> all by publike writings, and many others of the beſt learned of our Nation, both Prieſts, and lay-men I could name, who are of my opinion; and if it were not for the clamors, threatnings, and violent proceedings of our Aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, (I meane not Proteſtants) they vvould publikely profeſſe as much as I haue done: and as for the State of France, what opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion they be of, it is manifeſt. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that Doctrine of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aſquez</hi> concerning probable opinions may bee very wel ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed to this my doctrine, howſoeuer this Author falſely ſuppoſing the Doctrine for
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:19699:7"/>
the Popes power to depoſe Princes to be defined, would gladly perſwade our Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Catholikes to the contrarie.</p>
            <p n="5">5 <hi>Fourthly,</hi> I ſhewed in that booke, that ſeeing the <hi>Pope</hi> is not the Church, but onely a principall member thereof, their is to bee made a great diſtinction betweene the facts, and practiſes of <hi>Popes,</hi> and betweene the facts and practiſe of the Church: neither is the practiſe of many <hi>Popes,</hi> to bee accounted the practiſe of the Church, vnleſſe by the vvhole Church it be allowed, as that opinion and practiſe for the Popes power to depoſe Princes, and to inflict temporall puniſhments by way of coërtion neuer was: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore although it be, and hath beene, the more common opinion of Catholikes for ſome ages paſt, that the Pope hath au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to depoſe, yet that it is certaine, and not to bee contradicted, but to bee beleeued as a point of faith, and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary not to be accounted an opinion, but rather an hereſie, is altogether falſe. To the <hi>Councell</hi> of <hi>Lateran,</hi> which but of late yeares hath been vrged, and that onely by ſome few, becauſe <hi>Suarez</hi> did onely barely relate it, and not vrge the wordes
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:19699:8"/>
thereof, I did remit him to the <hi>Preface</hi> of my <hi>Apologelicall Anſwere,</hi> wherein I largely diſcourſed of the Decree of that Councel. But becauſe this Author ſeemeth to ſtand much thereon, as the chiefe pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar and ground of his pretended defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, I will at large in my Anſwere to his Reply treate of that Councell, and ſatisfie all the cauils (which neuertheleſſe ſhould bee cleere demonſtrations, if this Author did intend to proue his purpoſe) vvhich hee hath taken out of D. <hi>Singletons,</hi> or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Fa: Leſsius</hi> his Diſcuſſion of the Decree of that Councell, and I will ſhew, that it cannot be ſufficiently proued, <hi>firſt,</hi> that the Councell by thoſe words, <hi>tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Lord,</hi> did intend to include Soueraign Princes; <hi>ſecondly,</hi> that although it did by thoſe words vnderſtand Soueraigne Princes, yet that it did not ſuppoſe, that the Pope had authoritie to depoſe Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Princes; &amp; <hi>thirdly,</hi> that although it did ſuppoſe it, yet it did not ſuppoſe it as a point of faith, and an vndoubted doctrine, but at the moſt as probable opinion, ſo that from the authoritie of this Councel it can not bee conuinced, that it is a point of faith or an vndoubted doctrine, that the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:19699:8"/>
Pope hath authoritie to depoſe Soueraign Princes.</p>
            <p n="6">6 <hi>Laſtly,</hi> thou maiſt perceiue (Good Reader) what ſtrange paradoxes this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor dare aduenture to maintaine by this, that he bluſheth not to affirme, &amp; would cunningly perſwade our State, that my manner of handling this controuerſie pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably, concerning the Popes authoritie to depoſe Princes &amp;c. <hi>is dangerous &amp; pernici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to his Maieſtie,</hi> and therefore, <hi>that my books deſerue to be prohibited, no leſſe in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land then Rome, and that wiſe men in the parts where hee is, doe greatly maruell, how it can ſtand with the wiſedome of his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Councell to permit them to bee printed and publiſhed in England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7 But if this Author had either ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely or entirely related my opinion, or elſe had put in minde the Reader againſt what kinde of Aduerſaries I doe oppoſe, he would preſently haue perceiued, that it is too apparantly, &amp; ſhamefully vntrue, that my manner of handling this queſtion probably is dangerous and pernicious to <hi>his Maieſtie,</hi> as this Author doth endeuor to perſwade <hi>his Maieſty,</hi> not for any loue that he is knowne to beare vnto the State,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:19699:9"/>
but to the end, by all likelihood, that hee and ſuch like violent ſpirits, may vvrite more freely, and without being controu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led or contradicted by Catholikes, who, as hee is perſwaded doe little regard the writings, and opinions of Proteſtants con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this or any other Doctrine. For it may be dangerous to <hi>his Maieſtie</hi> to han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle a queſtion probably againſt one Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſarie, which will bee nothing dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to handle it probably againſt an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. As for example, if it were agreed vpon by all Catholikes, that the Pope hath no power to depoſe <hi>his Maieſtie,</hi> then it were dangerous to <hi>his Maieſtie,</hi> that any Catholike ſhould call this in que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, and diſpute it probably: but if on the contrarie ſide, all Catholikes ſhould agree in this, that it were certaine, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtionable, and a point of faith, that the Pope hath power to depoſe <hi>his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie,</hi> and to abſolue his Subiects of their allegiance, to command them to take armes againſt him, &amp;c. then if a Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like ſhould call this in queſtion, or, which is all one, diſpute it probably, and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine that it is not certaine that the Pope hath ſuch an authoritie, but it is queſtion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:19699:9"/>
and probable, that hee hath it not, no man of any ſenſe, or vnderſtanding can affirme, that ſuch a manner of diſputing this queſtion probably againſt thoſe Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries, who hold it for certaine, can be any way dangerous, or pernicious to <hi>his Maieſtie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8 Now behold the manner that I haue taken in handling this Controuerſie. <hi>Card. Bellarmin, Gretzer, Leſsius, Becanus, Suarez,</hi> and other Diuines, eſpecially of the Society of Ieſus, whom this Authour doth in euery ſteppe, as though he were their Creature, follow, haue laid this for a ſure and vndoubted ground, that it is a point of faith, and to be beleeued as cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, and vnder paine of eternall damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by all Catholikes, that the Pope hath power to depoſe Princes, to abſolue Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects from their Allegiance, and thereupon to commaund them to beare Armes, and raiſe tumults againſt their Prince ſo depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. So that you ſee, that they already haue layd the danger, and vndoubted o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrow to his Maieſties perſon and Crowne, if the Pope ſhould perchance depoſe him, in that they affirme, that all Catholikes are bound in conſcience to
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:19699:10"/>
forſake him, and to fulfill the Popes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund, to the deſtruction of <hi>His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties</hi> perſon and State. This Doctrine, to wit; that it is a point of Faith, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted principle of Catholike Religion, that the Pope hath power to depoſe Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and to inflict all temporal puniſhments by way of coercion, and that all Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes are bound in conſcience to forſake <hi>his Maieſtie,</hi> and to beare Armes againſt him, in caſe the Pope ſhould depoſe him, I haue taken vpon me, for two principall reaſons, to impugne, and do not doubt cleerely to maintaine the ſame againſt the clamours of this Authour, or any other whatſoeuer. My firſt reaſon was, for that it is againſt the truth and puritie of the Catholike Church, <hi>She being the piller and ground of truth,</hi> that doubtfull opinions, and which among Catholikes are onely in Controuerſie, and by the <hi>Parliament of Paris,</hi> haue beene condemned as <hi>ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, ſeditious, damnable,</hi> and <hi>Pernitious,</hi> ſhould be enforced vpon Engliſh Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes, as an vndoubted doctrine of the Catholike Faith, to the vtter ouerthrow of themſelues, and their whole poſterity, by me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> who are in no danger to looſe, but
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:19699:10"/>
rather to gaine temporall aduancement thereby.</p>
            <p n="9">9 My ſecond reaſon was, to aſſure <hi>His Maieſtie,</hi> that all Engliſh Catholikes may, according to the grounds of Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Religion, be true, and conſtant Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, and that notwithſtanding any ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of excommunication, or depriuation denounced, or to be denounced againſt <hi>his Maieſtie</hi> by the Pope, they may with a ſafe conſcience (marke well what I ſay) and alſo in practiſe they are bound, to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>here to <hi>his Maieſtie,</hi> and obey him in temporals, as ſtill remaining their true and lawfull <hi>Soueraigne,</hi> and to reſiſt any ſuch ſentence of Excommunication, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priuation. The reaſon wherefore I affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, that Catholikes might with a ſafe conſcience adhere to <hi>his Maieſtie,</hi> and reſiſt the Popes ſentence of depriuation, was, for that it is a probable opinion, and which with a ſafe conſcience, and without danger of Hereſie, error, or temerity, may bee embraced by Catholikes, that the Pope hath no authority to depoſe Princes, nor to inflict temporall puniſhments by way of coërcion, but that the laſt puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to which the Eccleſiaſticall power is extended, are onely Eccleſiaſticall and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:19699:11"/>
ſpiritual cenſures. Wherefore, that which this Author affirmeth, that I confeſſe, that it is probable, that the Pope can depoſe Princes is vntrue, vnleſſe he meane that I confeſſe it for diſputation ſake, or as we vſually ſay, <hi>Dato non conceſſo, it being giuen, not graunted,</hi> for that it maketh no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing for, or againſt the queſtion which is in hand. Therefore poſitiuely I neither affirme it, nor deny it, neither with that part of the contradiction, <hi>Whether it bee probable, that the Pope can depoſe, and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be probable, that the Oath may not be taken,</hi> doe I intermeddle: but whereas our Aduerſaries doe with ſo great violence mayntaine, that it is certaine, and an vndoubted doctrine of Faith, that the Pope can depoſe, and that the Oath cannot bee taken, I at this preſent doe affirme the contrary, <hi>That it is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable, that the Pope cannot depoſe, and that the Oath may lawfully be taken.</hi> Neither doe I, as this Authour impoſeth vpon me, take <hi>probable</hi> in that ſenſe, as <hi>Cicero</hi> in his Paradoxes did take it, when he affirmed, <hi>That nothing is ſo incredible, which by argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing may not be made probable,</hi> taking <hi>proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,</hi> for that which hath ſom ſhew or color of probability, or do I take <hi>probable</hi> for that
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:19699:11"/>
which I hold for <hi>probable,</hi> howſoeuer ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurde it be, (as this Authour abſurdly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmeth, that without doubt I doe) but I doe take <hi>probable</hi> in that ſenſe, as Diuines doe take a <hi>probable opinion</hi> and which may be followed with a ſafe conſcience, as I declared out of <hi>Vaſquez,</hi> and hereafter a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this Authour, and his confuſed de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of <hi>probable,</hi> which ſerueth onely to intangle the conſciences of the ſimple, I will more at large declare, in which ſenſe no Hereſie or erroneous doctrine can bee made <hi>probable,</hi> the contrary being deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the Church, as this doctrin for the Popes power to depoſe neuer was, but hath euer beene impugned by Catholike Writers vpon ſufficient grounds, and now lately condemned by the State of France, as pernicious and damnable doctrine.</p>
            <p n="10">10 But the ſecond and principall rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, which I brought for the ſecuring of <hi>his Maieſtie,</hi> and which this Author <hi>T. F.</hi> fraudulently concealeth, wherefore Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Catholikes not onely may in ſpecula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for the reaſon aforeſaide, but alſo in <hi>practiſe are bound,</hi> to adhere to <hi>his Maieſty,</hi> and to reſiſt the Popes ſentence of depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, was, for that, ſuppoſing ſpecula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuely
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:19699:12"/>
it be vncertaine, whether the Pope hath any ſuch power to depoſe a King, or no, it is an vndoubted rule among Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers, and grounded vpon the light of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and principles of Diuinity, that <hi>in cauſa dubia, ſiue incerta, melior eſt conditio poſſidentis. In a doubtfull and diſputable caſe the ſtate of him that is in poſſeſsion is the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter:</hi> And againe, <hi>Cum ſunt iura partium obſcura fauendum eſt reo potius, quàm acto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri, VVhen it is vnknowne, which of the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties that are in ſuite hath right, the defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant is to bee preferred before the plaintiffe.</hi> Seeing therefore that from the very firſt beginning of this Controuerſie, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the authority of Popes, and immuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Kings; that is, from the time of <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory</hi> the ſeuenth, who was the firſt Pope that challenged vnto him this temporall power ouer Kinges, this authority of the Pope to depoſe Kinges (call it temporall or ſpirituall, as you pleaſe) hath beene vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine, diſputable, and euer contradic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Catholikes, both Kinges and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, and therefore it cannot be ſaid that the Pope was euer in poſſeſſion of this au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, (although we ſhould grant, that power, right, or authority may be ſaid to
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:19699:12"/>
be poſſeſſed in that ſenſe as poſſeſſion is taken in Law, whereof in my Anſwere to this Authors Reply, I wil more at large diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe) it conſequently followeth, that what opinion ſoeuer any Catholike fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low <hi>ſpeculatiuely,</hi> concerning the Popes power to depoſe, yet in <hi>practiſe,</hi> vntill this Controuerſie, concerning the Popes au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to depoſe Kings, and the immunity of Kings not to be depoſed, ſhall be deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, as yet it is not, he cannot with a good conſcience endeuour to thruſt out a King ſo depoſed from the Kingdome, or Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions which he lawfully poſſeſſeth. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in the end of my Apologie I wrote theſe expreſſe words, of which alſo in my Epiſtle Dedicatory to his <hi>Holineſſe</hi> I made mentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>And therfore if eyther Pope, Prince, or any other forainer, ſhould attempt to thruſt an hereticall Prince out of the Kingdome which he poſſeſſeth; this Controuerſie concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the depoſition of Princes being vndeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, he ſhould contrary to the rules of Iuſtice do himſelfe moſt manifeſt wrong. And much more a Subiect cannot be excuſed from ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt treaſon, what opinion ſo uer hee doth ſpeculatiuely maintain concerning the Popes temporall power, who practically vnder colour
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:19699:13"/>
perchance of deuotion to the See Apoſtolike, not duly alſo conſidering the bond of his Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance towards his Soueraigne, ſhould en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuour to thruſt his lawfull Prince out of his Kingdome which he poſſeſſeth, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding any Excommunication, or ſentence of depriuation denounced by the Pope againſt him.</hi> Wherefore it is apparant, that in practiſe I taught it to bee abſolutely falſe, that the Pope hath authority to depoſe Princes.</p>
            <p n="11">11 Conſider now <hi>(good Reader) first</hi> the vnſincere dealing of this Author, who concealeth the cheefeſt part of my opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in ſecuring <hi>his Maieſtie</hi> of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant loyalty and allegiance, wherein all his Catholique Subiects are in conſcience bound vnto him, that thereby hee may cauſe <hi>his Maieſtie</hi> to be iealous of my fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delitie, and to account me no good Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect, as this Authour falſely affirmeth, that I am neither a good Subiect, nor a good Catholike, or Childe of the Church. But I truſt in God, that it will appeare to all men, that <hi>Inſurrexerunt in me teſtes iniqui, &amp; mentita eſt iniquitas ſibi,</hi> That <hi>falſe wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes are riſen vp againſt me, and wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe hath belyed her ſelfe;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>al.</hi> 26.</note> and that I will e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:19699:13"/>
prooue my ſelfe to bee both a good Subiect to <hi>his Maiestie,</hi> and alſo a dutifull child of the Catholike Church.</p>
            <p n="12">12 <hi>Secondlie,</hi> conſider the reaſon, why this Authour is ſo greatly offended, that I at this preſent doe onely take in hand (by anſwering probably all the arguments which on the contrary ſide are to be obie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted) to ſhew, that it is at leaſt-wiſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable, that the Pope hath no authority to depoſe Princes; and conſequently, that any man may with a probable and ſafe conſcience take the Oath; (for that the doctrine concerning the Popes authority to depoſe, is by this Authours owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, the maine queſtion betwixt him and me, and the cheefe ground wherefore the Oath is iudged to be vnlawfull.) His reaſon therefore is, for that hee ſaw right well, what great aduantage I had againſt him, and what little aduantage hee had againſt me, in arguing or rather anſwering in this ſort, and therefore he calleth it in heat of his zeale, <hi>The moſt deuoliſh deuice that any man could inuent.</hi> And truly if I ſhould at this firſt beginning haue treated of this Controuerſie in any other manner, then by handling it <hi>probably,</hi> in that ſenſe
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:19699:14"/>
as I haue declared, I might worthily haue beene cenſured of great imprudency, in giuing my Aduerſary more aduantage a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt mee then was needfull. For this is the State of the queſtion, <hi>whether it can be cleerely conuinced by the authority of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scriptures, Ancient Fathers, Generall Councels, or by neceſſary inferences from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them, as our Aduerſaries pretend to conuince, that it is an vndoubted doctrine of Faith, and the contrary not be defended by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Catholike, that the Pope hath power to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe Princes; and conſequently that the oath cannot lawfully be taken.</hi> This is the queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: Marke now the aduantage I haue: for <hi>firſt</hi> I am not to prooue but onely to aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer: to defend, not to oppoſe: <hi>Secondlie,</hi> it is ſufficient for me, that my anſwers be onely probable; but there Replyes muſt not bee onely probable, but alſo conuin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing, and which with any probabilitie cannot bee anſwered. So that if I ſhould goe about at the firſt to proue my opinion to be moſt true, which my aduerſary affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth not to be queſtionable, I ſhould, as it is euident, greatly diſaduantage my ſelfe. For in ſuch Controuerſies, as are ſo vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently maintained by the Aduerſary, that
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:19699:14"/>
he will not grant the contrary part to bee queſtionable, it is neceſſary to proceed by degrees; firſt to make the thing queſtion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and diſputable, which the aduerſe part will not haue to be called in queſtion: and after this is once agreed vpon, then to examine whether opinion be the trueſt. For perchance it may fall out, that as the opinion for the immaculate Conception of our <hi>B. Lady,</hi> before <hi>Scotus</hi> did oppoſe himſelfe therein againſt S. <hi>Thomas</hi> and his followers, was ſcarſe accounted probable, yet afterwards it was daily more and more followed, ſo that now it is eſteemed to be the farre more true opinion: and as <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phonſus Salmeron,</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">In cap. <hi>5.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Rem. diſp. <hi>51.</hi> Sect. D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> inde.</note> and <hi>Fa. Suarez</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Tom. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> diſp. <hi>3.</hi> ſec.</note> doe affirme, <hi>Agreed vpon by the conſent almoſt of the Vniuerſall Church, and of the Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall writers, Biſhops, Religious Orders, and Vniuerſities;</hi> and as that opinion, which holdeth that the Pope hath not power to diſpence in the ſolemne vow of religious chaſtitie, neither in any lawfull marriage before it be conſummate, is accounted by very many learned men to bee the farre truer opinion, notwithſtanding the prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of many Popes to the contrary: So it may fall out, that in proceſſe of time this
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:19699:15"/>
opinion that denieth the Popes authority to depoſe Princes, may bee embraced by almoſt all Eccleſiaſticall Writers, Biſhops, Religious Orders, and Vniuerſities, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the practiſe of many Popes, and the vehement oppoſition of the Ieſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ites at this preſent time to the contrary.</p>
            <p n="13">13 <hi>Thirdly,</hi> conſider how little behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding are Engliſh Catholikes to this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor <hi>T. F.</hi> who will needes enforce them euen with the temporall ouerthrowe of themſelues, and of their whole poſteritie to defend that doctrine to bee of faith, which the State of France hath condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for <hi>ſcandalous, ſeditious, damnable,</hi> and <hi>pernicious,</hi> and alſo endeuoureth to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade <hi>his Maieſty,</hi> that no Catholick can, according to the grounds of Catholike re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, be a true, and loyall Subiect to <hi>his Maieſtie,</hi> but at the Popes pleaſure, or which is all one, ſo long onely as the Pope ſhall not depoſe him, which hee may doe at his pleaſure. But we haue great affiance in <hi>his Maiesties</hi> ſingular wiſedome, and clement diſpoſition, wherof we haue had both by <hi>his Maieſties</hi> gracious Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation,<note place="margin">Publiſhed after the diſcouerie of the <hi>Gun-powder</hi> trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</note> publike bookes, and effectuall deeds ſufficient triall, that he will not bee
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:19699:15"/>
drawne by the falſe ſuggeſtion of this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, (who would haue all Catholikes to be of the ſame violent ſpirit as hee is) to haue all his Catholike Subiects, in the ſame degree of iealouſie, but that he will euer make a diſtinction betwixt them, who are his true hearted Subiects, and moſt loyall in all temporall affaires, and wil aduenture all, that they haue, and are, in defence of <hi>his Maieſties</hi> Royall perſon, and dignitie, againſt any ſentence of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priuation whatſoeuer, which ſhall be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced againſt him by the Pope,<note n="i" place="margin">For ſo much did thoſe 13. Reuerend Prieſts M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>D. Biſhop,</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Colleto</hi> &amp; the reſt by a publik Act bear in date the la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of Ianuary 1602. pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>miſe to <hi>Queene Eli<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>zabeth:</hi> the copie wher of thou maiſt ſee my Appen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dix, page 346.</note> (aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring themſelues, that it is conformable to the grounds of Catholike Religion which they profeſſe, and not repugnant to that ſpirituall obedience wherein they ſtand bound to the ſupreme Paſtour of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Church) and thoſe other Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes, who thinking it to bee a point of faith, that the Pope hath authoritie to dethrone Soueraigne Princes, will onely defend <hi>his Maiestie,</hi> and yeeld him tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall obedience, vntill the Pope, after his ſentence of depriuation ſhall command them the contrarie. And therefore let this Author <hi>T. F.</hi> aſſure himſelfe, that all his clamorous words, and threatning ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:19699:16"/>
ſhall nothing diſcourage mee from defending the truth, neither am I preſt on, to write againſt him or any other, to ſhew my wit, as hee falſely affirmeth, or for hope of any temporall lucre, or prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but meerely and ſincerely for the loue I beare to God, Religion, the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like truth, my Prince, and Countrey: for which cauſes I neither am, nor euer vvill be aſhamed to be preſt on, to write againſt this <hi>T. F.</hi> or any other ſuch like Authour, who liuing in other countreyes, and out of danger to looſe any thing, but rather in hope to obtaine aduancement by their writings, will preſſe Engliſh Catholikes to defend, with danger of looſing all that they haue, &amp; of incurring their <hi>Soueraigne</hi> his high diſpleaſure, that Doctrine to bee of faith, which the State of France ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counteth <hi>damnable,</hi> and enioyneth the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites vnder paine of treaſon to preach the contrarie, as thou ſhalt perceiue by the Decree, which followeth, which is true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tranſlated out of the French copie, prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at Paris, vvhich I haue conferred with this Engliſh.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="decree">
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:19699:16"/>
            <head>A DECREE <hi>Of the Court of Parliament made the</hi> 26. <hi>and executed the</hi> 27. <hi>of Iune</hi> 1614. AGAINST A Booke printed at Cologne this preſent yeere, entituled, <hi>Franciſci Suarez Granatenſis Societatis Ieſu Doctoris Theologi Defenſio fidei Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicae, et Apoſtolicae aduerſus An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glicanae ſectae errores,</hi> containing di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers maximes, and propoſitions repugnant to the Soueraigne po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of Kings, ordained and eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed by God, the ſafetie of their perſons, and the peace and tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quilitie of their States.</head>
            <head type="sub">The place ❀ where are ſet the Kings armes.</head>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>At Paris.</hi>
               </dateline>
By <hi>F. Morel,</hi> and <hi>Peter Mettayer,</hi> the Kings Printers and Stationers in Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. 1614. <hi>With his Maieſties priuiledge.</hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:19699:17"/>
Extracted out of the Regiſters of the Parliament.</opener>
            <p>THE Court of the great Chamber, <hi>Tournelle,</hi> and of the Edict aſſembled, hauing viewed the Booke printed at Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logne this preſent yeare, entituled, <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſci Suarez Granatenſis, è Societate Ieſu, Doctoris Theologi, Defenſio Fidei Catholicae et Apoſtolicae, aduerſus Anglicanae ſectae er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rores,</hi> containing in the third book <hi>Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> 23. pages 376. 79. 80. 82. <hi>Chapter</hi> 29. pages 310, 11. 12. 13. 14. 15. 16. 17. 18. 19. 20. <hi>Chapter</hi> 6. page 834. <hi>Chap.</hi> 8. pag. 844. and in other places many propoſitions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Soueraigne power of Kings or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained and eſtabliſhed by God, the peace and tranquilitie of their States, and that it is lawfull for their Subiects and ſtrangers to attempt againſt their Perſons. Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of the Kings Atturney Generall.</p>
            <p>All this being conſidered,</p>
            <p>The ſaid Court hath declared, and doth declare the Propoſitions, and Maximes contained in the ſaid booke, to be ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous, and ſeditious, tending to the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion of States, and to induce the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects of Kings, and Soueraigne Princes,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:19699:17"/>
and others to attempt againſt their Sacred Perſons, and the ſpeeches mentioning <hi>King Chlowis,</hi> and <hi>Philip</hi> the faire to bee falſe and ſlanderous, and <hi>hath alſo ordained and doth ordaine, that the ſaid Booke of Suarez be burned in the Court of the Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace by the Executioner of high Iuſtice.</hi> And it hath, and doth inhibite, and forbid all ſellers of Bookes, and Printers, to print, fell, or diſperſe any of the ſaid bookes, and alſo all other perſons of whatſoeuer cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling or condition they bee, to haue, to write out, to retaine, or to teach in Schooles, or elſewhere, or to Diſpute the ſaid Maximes, or propoſitions. It alſo or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daineth according to the Decree of the 8 of Iune 1610. that the Decree of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultie of Diuinitie made vpon the 4. of Iune the ſame yeere, concerning the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newing of the Doctrinall Cenſure of the ſaid Facultie bearing date the yeere 1408. confirmed by the Councell of Conſtance, together with this preſent Decree, as alſo thoſe of the yeere 1578 &amp; 95. ſhall yeare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be read the fourth day of Iune, as vvell in the ſaid Facultie, as in the Colledge of the Prieſts, and Schollers of the Colledge of Clermont, and of the foure Orders of
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:19699:18"/>
begging Fryars: And that at the requeſt of the Kings Attourney General informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions ſhall bee taken of the contrauenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons againſt the ſaid Decrees, and Prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitions made againſt writing, hauing, or keeping the like bookes. Giuen in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the 26. day of Iune 1614.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Signed. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>oiſin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Furthermore it is Decreed, that the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, <hi>Ignace Armand,</hi> Rector in this Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, <hi>Cotton, Frorton,</hi> and <hi>Sirmund,</hi> ſhall bee ſummoned the firſt day to the Court, and to them ſhall be ſhewed, that contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to their declaration, and Decree of their General of the yeare 1610. the Book of <hi>Suarez</hi> hath been printed, and brought into this Citie, impugning the authoritie of the King, and againſt the ſafety of his Perſon, and State: and they ſhall bee en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioined to cauſe their Generall to renew the ſaid Decree, and to publiſh it, and to bring in an Act thereof within theſe ſix monethes: and to prouide, that no Books containing ſuch damnable, and pernici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous propoſitions bee made, or publiſhed by any of their company: and alſo they
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:19699:18"/>
ſhall be enioyned in their Sermons to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort the people to the Doctrine contrarie to the ſaid propoſitions. Otherwiſe the Court will proceed againſt the tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours as men guiltie of Treaſon, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbers of the publike quietnes.</p>
            <p>This aboue ſaid Decree, and the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed were pronounced in the preſence of the <hi>Fathers, Ignace Armand, Charles de la Toure</hi> in the abſence of <hi>Peter Cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, Fronton da Duc,</hi> and <hi>Iames Sir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mund.</hi> And the Decree was put in exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution before the great Stayres of the Pallace the 27. of Iune. 1614.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>
               <hi>A Copy</hi> of a Letter, which is ſaid to be written by the <hi>moſt Reuerend, and right Honorable Lord,</hi> the Popes Nuncio <hi>at</hi> Bruſſels, <hi>to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
               </hi> George Birket <hi>Arch-presbyter then liuing.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Very Reuerend Sir, and as a brother moſt beloued in Chriſt.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THere came into the Citie of <hi>Rome</hi> a Theologicall Diſputation concerning the Oath of Allegiance, the third worke
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:19699:19"/>
publiſhed vnder the name of <hi>Widdrington.</hi> After it was there diligently examined, our moſt <hi>Holy Lord</hi> declared, that hee in no wiſe accepted of the Dedication of that booke, and that he thought the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of it was neither a child of the church, nor a Catholike; and further, that all Catholikes ſhould abſtaine from the reading thereof. Of theſe things I was certified ſome few daies ſince by let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the congregation of the vniuerſall Romane Inquiſition by the commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>his Holineſſe,</hi> to the end that I ſhould write thereof eſpecially to your Reuerence, that you may ſignifie the ſame to the Catholikes there, and according to your wiſdome make it known vnto them. God defend your Reuerence with his heauenly cuſtodie. From Bruxells the 26. Nouemb. 1613.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Of your Reuerence moſt louing and reſpectiue</signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>To the Letters, which are ſpread abroad among vs no name is ſubſcribed.</p>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <div type="address">
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:19699:19"/>
            <head>A COPY OF ROGER WID<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DRINGTONS <hi>Purgation.</hi> To the moſt Holy and moſt Bleſſed Father <hi>Pope</hi> PAVL <hi>the fifth,</hi> ROGER WID<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DRINGTON an Engliſh Catholike wiſheth euerlaſting happines.</head>
            <p n="1">1 THere came vnto my hands ſome few daies ſince <hi>(moſt bleſſed Father)</hi> a certaine Decree of the Sacred Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of the right Honourable Cardinals of the Holy Romane Church, who are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted for the examining of bookes, dated the 16. day of March of this preſent yeere 1614, and printed in Rome by the printer of the Apoſtolicall Chamber, vvherein two bookes written by me in ſinceritie, and ſimplicitie of heart, are by name, but yet onely in generall words without na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming any crime either in particular or in generall, at which many doe maruell, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together condemned and forbidden <hi>by the commandement of your Holineſſe.</hi> And the Author of them vnleſſe he ſhall forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with purge himſelfe, is threatned to bee puniſhed with Cenſures, and other Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall puniſhments,</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb facs="tcp:19699:20"/>2 But what manner of purging <hi>your Holineſſe</hi> doth expect at my hands, who am the Authour of thoſe Bookes, and of what crime I ought to purge my ſelfe (ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that in this Decree there is no crime either in particular, or in generall obiect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed againſt me of which I ſhould purge my ſelfe, neither is my conſcience priuie to any crime for the making, or publiſhing of thoſe bookes) I can not verily in any wiſe perceiue. I know that certaine Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors miſinterpreting my words, haue in their publike writings falſely, and very iniuriouſly, not to ſpeake a more heinous word (I pray God to forgiue them) im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peached me of certaine crimes (by whoſe inſtigation I know not whether <hi>your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe</hi> hath beene mooued to condemne thoſe bookes) but conſidering that both they are my Aduerſaries in this contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſie, and that they are mooued, as I thinke, rather by affection, then by ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lide reaſon, and alſo that they do foulely corrupt my words, and wreſt them to a moſt bad ſenſe, and neuer intended by mee (as I could moſt cleerely demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate to <hi>your Holineſſe,</hi> if it vvere now a conuenient time) I doe not thinke, that
<pb facs="tcp:19699:20"/>
ſo great authoritie is to bee giuen, either to their ſayings or writings, of what lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, or dignitie ſo euer otherwiſe they be, that they are of force to binde mee, either to embrace their opinions, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally being grounded vpon ſo weake foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations, or not to defend my innocencie from their falſe accuſations in ſuch an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding great crime, as hereſie is.</p>
            <p n="3">3 And that <hi>your Holineſſe</hi> may cleere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perceiue, that I haue alreadie in theſe bookes, which are forbidden by your commandement, purged my ſelfe as much, as is ſufficient for a child of the Catholike Church, I thinke it neceſſarie to repeate againe with as much breuitie as may be in what manner I haue in thoſe bookes made profeſſion of the Catholike faith (which in my opinion aboundantly ſufficeth for the purging of my ſelfe from all imputation of hereſie, errour, or any other crime, which doth depend on theſe) and for what thing I made Suppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation to <hi>your Holineſſe</hi> in that <hi>Diſputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of the oath of Allegiance, that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by <hi>your Holineſſe</hi> may manifeſtly perceiue, that ſome perſons, not of the meaneſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, although perchance with the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:19699:21"/>
ſort of people they doe greatly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire my credite, yet they doe alſo bring <hi>your Holineſſe</hi> into no ſmall obloquy both among prudent Catholikes, and eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally among thoſe, who are Aduerſaries to the Catholike faith, whiles they are not afraid to diuulge, not ſo circumſpectly in my iudgement as is fitting, that <hi>your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe</hi> did in good earneſt auouch, <hi>that you thought the Authour of that Diſputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to bee neither a Catholike, nor a child of the Church</hi> (whereas the Author doth profeſſe himſelfe both to be a Catholike, and a child of the Catholike Romane Church, and ſubmitteth moſt humbly that Diſputation and all his other writings to the iudgement of the Holy Catholike Romane Church) <hi>neither that you would accept of the Dedication of that booke,</hi> whereas <hi>that Dedication,</hi> as it is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt by the Epiſtle of the Author writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to <hi>your Holineſſe,</hi> was onely a moſt <hi>humble Supplication</hi> of the Author, and of other Catholikes vnto <hi>your Holineſſe,</hi> that <hi>your Holineſſe,</hi> as being the ſupreme Paſtour of the Catholike Church, and whoſe office is to inſtruct, and confirme the ſheepe of Chriſt in the Catholike
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:19699:21"/>
faith, would bee pleaſed to inſtruct them in the Catholike faith, &amp; in thoſe things, which <hi>your Holineſſe</hi> had declared by your <hi>Breues</hi> to be cleerely repugnant to faith, and ſaluation. And that <hi>your Holineſſe</hi> did ſpeake the aforeſaid words, both of the Authour, and alſo of the Dedication, ſome here giue forth, that <hi>your Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> his Nuncius then reſiding at <hi>Bruſſels</hi> did ſignifie as much to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>George Birk<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t</hi> the Arch-prieſt, who was then liuing, and that the ſame <hi>Nuncius</hi> did withall af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme, <hi>that he was certified ſome few daies ſince of thoſe things</hi> (for ſo bee the expreſſe words of the <hi>Nuncius</hi> his Letters,<note n="a" place="margin">Theſe Let<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ters were dated at Bruſſels 26 Nouemb. 1613.</note> which are ſpred abroad among vs) <hi>by Letters of the Congregation of the holy Romane vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall Inquiſition by the commandement of your Holineſſe, to the end, that hee ſhould write thereof eſpecially to his Reuerence, that he according to his wiſedome ſhould ſignifie as much, and make it knowne here to Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4 Firſt therefore I the Author of thoſe Bookes did proteſt, <hi>That I compoſed them being mooued thereunto for the zeale of God, of Religion, and of my Countrey, and for other more particular reaſons,</hi> which I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated
<pb facs="tcp:19699:22"/>
in the beginning of thoſe Bookes, <hi>without any respect of worldly fauour, or fear, neither with any obſtinate mind, but onely to finde out the Catholike truth in this moſt weighty Controuerſie, which belongeth to the yeelding of obedience due by the Law of Chriſt to God, and Caeſar,</hi> to your Holineſſe, <hi>who is the ſupreame Paſtour in Earth of our ſoules, and to our</hi> King, his moſt excellent Maieſtie, <hi>who in temporals is onely inferior to GOD, and I did ſubmit moſt humbly</hi>
               <note place="margin">In Apolog. Lect<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> in fine.</note> 
               <hi>whatſoeuer was contained in them to the iudgement and cenſure of the Catholike Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Church, whoſe Childe I profeſſed my ſelfe to be, and if perchance any thing through ignorance had eſcaped me, which ſhould not bee approoued by her, I did diſprooue it, damne it, and would haue it for not writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten</hi>
               <note place="margin">In Diſp. in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e.</note>.</p>
            <p n="5">5 Beſides, I did <hi>profeſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">In Diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Cap. <hi>6. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 3.</hi> Num. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. &amp; ſeq.</note> 
               <hi>that with all due honour and reſpect I did reuerence all the Canons of the Catholike Church, although I did freely confeſſe, that betwixt the Catholike Church and the Pope, who is onely the firſt and principall member thereof, betwixt ſome Chapters or Decrees of the Cannon Law, and betwixt others, a great diſtinction was to be made, and neuertheleſſe I ſincerely affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med,
<pb facs="tcp:19699:22"/>
that to euery one, in his degree and place, I gaue dutifull, but not equall credit. For in the vaſt Corps of the Canon Law, and in the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>olumes of the Councels are contained, ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſayings, or aſſertions of the Ancient Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, or Decrees, or ſentences of Popes and Councels: and theſe are either doctrinall, and which are propounded as things to be beleeued by the faithfull, or elſe morall, and which in the external diſcipline of the Church, are commanded to be obſerued.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6 And firſt, <hi>I did acknowledge, that the doctrine which the Ancient Fathers either in expounding the Holy Scriptures, or in Questions belonging to Faith, haue with v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niforme conſent deliuered: I did alſo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly beleeue, as being certainly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, that it was inſpired by the Holie Ghoſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7 Secondly, <hi>I alſo with</hi> Melchior Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, <hi>and other Diuines affirmed, that the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine alſo of all the holie Fathers in thinges, which do not appertaine to Faith, may piouſly and probably be beleeued by Catholikes, yet that it ought not of neceſſity to be followed as certaine, and infallible.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8 Thirdly, <hi>I did profeſſe, that the definiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Generall Councels, lawfully aſſembled,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:19699:23"/>
and confirmed by the Pope, wherein any do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine is propounded to the whole Church, to be beleeued of al men as of Faith, are to bee receiued by Catholikes as infallible rules of Faith. Neuertheleſſe, I did freely affirme with the aforeſaid</hi> Melchior Canus, and Card. Bellarmine, <hi>that thoſe opini ns, which in the ſaid Councels are defined, or elſe ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed onely as probable, and thoſe aſſertions which either incidently, and by the way are inſerted, or for better declaration, or proofe of their deciſions bee produced, are ſometimes ſubiect to error, and may be Catholikes with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any wrong to the Catholike Faith bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iected. This withall obſeruing, of which alſo in other places I haue admoniſhed the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that although I, profeſſing my ſelfe to be a childe of the Catholike Romane Church, doe moſt willingly embrace whatſoeuer Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Councel confirmed by the Pope, which doe repreſent the Catholike Church, doe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound to the faithful as neceſſarily to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued of faith, and which certainely, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidently is knowne to bee the true ſenſe and meaning of the Councels: neuertheleſſe, I do not vndoubtedly beleeue euery doctrine which either</hi> Card. Bellarmine <hi>(ſpeaking with due reuerence) or any other Doctour, ſeeing they
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:19699:23"/>
are not appointed by God to be an vndoubted rule of the Catholike Faith, doe cry out to bee Catholike doctrine, to be the voyce of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Church, to bee the meaning of the Scriptures and Councels, if eſpecially ſome Catholike Doctours doe hold the contrary. Then truely, as it is meete, I doe reuerence with all dutifull reſpect, and I doe much at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute to their authority, but that all thoſe collections, which they in their iudgements doe imagine to be euidently concluded out of holy Scriptures or Councels (conſidering that oftentimes they are deceiued, and do deceiue, and what they haue written when they were younger, they may recall when they grow el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">For <hi>Car<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Bell.</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in his old age ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> recalled ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny thinges which he wrote wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> he was yon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ger, &amp; p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> chance h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> now being elder, will recall mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>) <hi>are to bee accounted for vndoubted aſſertions of faith, and the contrary opinion of other Catholikes to be rather eſteemed an hereſie then an opinion, this truly I cannot take in good part.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">9 <hi>Fourthly,</hi> concerning the Canons, or Decrees of Generall Councels belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to manners, and to the externall go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment of the Church, <hi>I promiſed to bee moſt ready to receiue willingly all thoſe De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees, which in places where I ſhall liue, ſhal be generally receiued; for theſe are properlie called the Decrees, or Canons of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like
<pb facs="tcp:19699:24"/>
or Vniuerſall Church which are by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon conſent admitted by the Vniuerſall Church. Neither doubtleſſe is any man bound to admit thoſe Lawes and precepts, which in the Country where he liueth, are not obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by the people, as according to the receiued opinion of Deuines, and Lawyers; I there af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed. And the ſame I there auouched, was to be vnderſtood proportionally of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees of Popes, and Prouinciall Councels. For as concerning the Popes definitions be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to faith, if he define without a Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Councell,</hi> I confeſſe, that I haue often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times auerred, <hi>that very many, eſpecially Ancient Diuines of the Vniuerſity of Paris,</hi> whoſe names I there related,<note place="margin">Cap. <hi>10.</hi> ſec. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. num. <hi>27.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>are of opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, that ſuch Definitions, vnleſſe they bee receiued by the Catholike Church, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Catholike Faith, are ſubiect to errour, whoſe opinion, both for the authority of ſo famous men, and alſo for the reaſons, and grounds, whereon that opinion is foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, I with later Deuines</hi> (to whoſe opinion alſo <hi>Card. Bellarmine</hi> himſelfe doth plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enough incline<note place="margin">Lib. <hi>2.</hi> de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oncil. cap. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>, howſoeuer he would ſeeme to auerre the contrary<note place="margin">Lib. <hi>4.</hi> de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>om. Pont. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p. <hi>2</hi> &amp; lib. de concil. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p. <hi>17.</hi>
               </note>) haue alſo oftentimes affirmed, <hi>is not to be condemned of hereſie, errour, or temerity,</hi> which alſo
<pb facs="tcp:19699:24"/>
now againe (ſpeaking with all dutiful ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion) I feare not to confirme.</p>
            <p n="10">10 <hi>Laſtly,</hi> concerning my Diſputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Oath, and the Dedication ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, which ſeemeth to be that ſtone of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, and rocke of ſcandall to ſome De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines, eſpecially of the Society of Ieſus, and to thoſe Catholikes who adhere to them, I cannot, to ſpeake vnfaignedly, in any wiſe, vnderſtand what can iuſtly bee obiected againſt it, or what fault I haue committed, either in making it, or elſe in dedicating it to <hi>your Holineſſe,</hi> of which I ſhould purge my ſelfe. For firſt of all, I the Authour of that Diſputation and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication, haue therein profeſſed; <hi>That I did not write it with any obſtinate minde, but in manner of an humble petition, ſincerelie,</hi> and for many reaſons which I there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſed, <hi>to informe</hi> your Holineſſe <hi>more fully, who as heere we thinke, hath not beene rightly informed of the reaſons, for vvhich Engliſh Catholickes are of opinion, that the Oath may lawfully bee taken; and for this cauſe I did dedicate it to</hi> your Holineſſe, <hi>that after you had carefully examined all the reaſons, for which Engliſh Catholikes doe think the Oath may lawfully be taken,</hi> your
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:19699:25"/>
Holineſſe <hi>might prouide both for their ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall and temporall ſafety, as according to your fatherly wiſedome, and charitie ſhould be thought moſt conuenient.</hi> And therefore, as in the end of that Diſputation I affirmed, <hi>I did faithfully ſet downe all the cheefeſt ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, which are vſually alleaged as well againſt the taking of the oath, as in fauour thereof, neither did I intend to affirme any thing of my owne opinion, but onely as repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting the perſons of them, who of ſet pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe doe publikely maintaine, that the Oath either may, or may not lawfully be taken, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing it to the fatherly care of</hi> your Holines, <hi>that when you haue beene fully informed of the whole progreſſe of the matter, and haue diligently examined all the reaſons, for which Engliſh Catholikes, obeying the Kings com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund, haue taken the Oath, you will bee pleaſed particularly to approoue them, or to condemne them, that Catholikes in this ſo moſt weightie a matter, which doth ſo neere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly concerne the prerogatiue of your ſpirituall Authority, and of his</hi> Maieſties Royaltie, <hi>being fearefull to reſiſt</hi> your Holineſſe <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept declared in</hi> your Breues, <hi>and alſo beeing deſirous to obey, as much as with a ſafe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience they may,</hi> his Maieſties <hi>commaund,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:19699:25"/>
may clearely perceiue, which particular clau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of the Oath they are bound to admit, and which they are bound to reiect, and may in plaine and expreſſe termes without any am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biguitie of wordes be instructed by</hi> your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, <hi>in what manner they may ſatisfie their owne conſcience,</hi> your Holineſſe <hi>will, and alſo</hi> his Maieſties <hi>deſire concerning all the particular partes of the Oath. For as they are very ready to hazzard their whole temporall eſtate, and alſo to looſe their liues for the Catholike faith, which by the Church (to whom this office belongeth to define mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Faith, and not to priuate Doctours, who may deceiue, and be deceiued) is decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to be truly the Catholike faith, ſo doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe they are vnwilling to expoſe themſelues, and their whole Family and Poſterity, which this our age doth ſo much labour to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uance, to eminent danger of their temporall vtter ruine, onely for opinions, although they be maintained by the greater, and better part of Deuines, ſo that others, although farre fewer in number, doe defend the contrary. But as they are deſirous with all their hearts to obey</hi> your Holineſſe <hi>in ſpirituall matters, and in thoſe things, which cannot be omitted
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:19699:26"/>
without ſinne: ſo alſo they might iuſtly thinke themſelues to be more hardly vſed, then chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren are wont by their Parents, if, eſpecially in theſe times, wherein by reaſon of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Faith, which they profeſſe, they haue greeuouſly incurred</hi> his Maieſties <hi>high diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure, who is of a contrary Religion, they ſhould without ſufficient reaſon be forbidden to giue that temporall Allegiance to his</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, <hi>which they thinke by the Law of Christ to be due vnto him, hauing alwaies before their eies that commaund of</hi> Chriſt our Sauiour, Render to Caeſar the thinges that are Caeſars, and to God the thinges that are Gods.</p>
            <p n="11">11 And that <hi>your Holineſſe</hi> may yet more cleerely perceiue, that this my Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of the Oath (which is rather to be called a moſt humble Supplication to <hi>your Holineſſe</hi>) was written in manner of an humble Petition, I thinke it not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe to repeate alſo word by word theſe very laſt wordes of my Epiſtle to <hi>your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="12">12 <hi>This therefore</hi> (moſt Holie Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) <hi>is our moſt humble Supplication to</hi> your Holineſſe, <hi>Firſt, that your Holineſſe will bee
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:19699:26"/>
pleaſed to examine diligently the reaſons, for which our Engliſh Catholikes doe thinke the Oath may lawfully be taken, and wherof they are perſwaded</hi> your Holineſs <hi>is not yet right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly informed:</hi> Secondly <hi>that after you haue throughly examined them, you will vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe in regard of your Paſtorall carefulneſſe to inſtruct them, which parts of the Oath are, (I do not ſay only according to a probable opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of ſome Doctors, but according to Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Doctrine, neceſſarily to bee beleeued by all Chriſtians) repugnant to faith and ſaluation, and therefore can not be taken by any Catholike with a ſafe, and probable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience:</hi> Thirdly, <hi>that if</hi> your Holineſſe <hi>ſhal finde, that you haue not beene rightly infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of thoſe reaſons, for which our Engliſh Catholikes doe think, that the Oath may law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully be taken, and that therefore they haue not in a matter of ſo great weight proceeded raſhly, and vnaduiſedly, you will be pleaſed to receiue them, and their Prieſts into your an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient fauour, and that if they, or any of them haue, not through their own fault but throgh the indiſcreete zeale of others ſuffered any loſſe, or detriment in their good names, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther waies, it may be reſtored againe to them
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:19699:27"/>
in that beſt manner, as ſhall ſeeme conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to the charitie, iuſtice, and wiſedome of</hi> your Holineſſe.</p>
            <p n="13">13. Now what there is contained in this our humble Petition, againſt which <hi>your Holineſſe</hi> hath iuſt cauſe to take ſo high diſpleaſure, that you will not accept thereof, I remit to the iudgement of indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent men, but eſpecially of <hi>your Holines.</hi> For by that, which wee haue ſayd, it doth manifeſtly appeare, that this diſputation of the Oath was for that end compoſed by me, to informe <hi>your Holineſſe</hi> (who is the Supreme Paſtor of the Catholike Church, and to whom Chriſt our Lord hath giuen charge to feed his ſheepe, not onely with precepts and Cenſures, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo with the word of Doctrine, and to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct them in the Catholike faith) truely of our ſtate, and to propound vnto <hi>your Holineſſe</hi> ſincerely and with all duetifull ſubmiſſion thoſe doubts, and difficulties, which both to my ſelfe, and other Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes doe occurre about this new Oath, which is commaunded by <hi>his Maieſty,</hi> forbidden by <hi>your Holineſſe,</hi> and dayly ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by almoſt all Catholikes of the better
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:19699:27"/>
ſort, to whom it is tendred, yea euen by thoſe, who haue the Ieſuites for their di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectours, howſoeuer theſe Fathers doe in outward ſhew ſeeme to condemne the ſame; that after <hi>your Holineſſe</hi> had duely examined the reaſons, and arguments, which are vſually alledged on both ſides, againſt, and for the taking of the Oath, you would bee pleaſed to ſatisfie our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, and to make knowne vnto vs, what parts of the Oath may according to the principles of the Catholike faith bee lawfully, and what parts may not lawfully bee taken, and laſtly to declare vnto vs, which bee thoſe many things, which <hi>your Holineſſe,</hi> being not rightly informed by ſome, as wee imagine, hath affirmed in <hi>your Breeues</hi> to bee cleerely repugnant to faith and ſaluation, for no man, be he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo great an enemy to the Oath, dare auouch, that all things contayned in the Oath are repugnant to faith and ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p n="14">14. Now I beſeech <hi>your Holineſſe</hi> to iudge, <hi>firſt,</hi> whether I the authour of thoſe bookes, who haue profeſſed my ſelfe to bee a Catholike, and a child of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:19699:28"/>
Romane Church, and haue ſubiec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted all my writtings to her iudgment, and Cenſure, with that ſubmiſſion, that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer ſhould not bee approoued by her I would diſprooue, condemne, and haue it for not written, ought bee adiudged by the Supreme Paſtour, and Father of the Catholike Church to bee no Catholike, nor a child of the Catholike Church. If I bee no Catholike, doubtleſſe I muſt bee an heretike, &amp; defend obſtinately (ſeeing that hereſie cannot be without obſtinacy) ſome Doctrine contrary to the Catholike faith. But I (to ſay nothing at this time of the Doctrine, which I mainetained in thoſe bookes, which if it were cleerely hereticall, why did not that ſacred Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation condemne thoſe bookes as he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticall?) proteſted to write nothing ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinately, but with an humble and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſiue mind, and ready to recall my er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, as ſoone as I ſhould perceiue that I had erred in any thing. I confeſſe indeed that I may erre, but by God his aſſiſtance I will neuer be an heretik. And if perchance in any thing I haue erred, it is no errour of malice, or obſtinacy, but of ignorance and
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:19699:28"/>
infirmity: For I will neuer by God his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, wittingly and willingly defend a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing at all, which I ſhall know to bee contrary to ſound Doctrine, or to the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike faith.</p>
            <p n="15">15. Secondly, concerning that, which ſome men, to no ſmall ſcandall to Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Religion, and to the great diſgrace of the See Apoſtolike, eſpecially among thoſe who be Aduerſaries to the Catholike Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, doe giue out, that <hi>your Holineſſe</hi> ſhould ſay, <hi>that you would not accept the Dedication of my diſputation concerning the Oath,</hi> or rather the moſt humble Supplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of me, and of other Catholikes, as I haue ſhewed before, this onely at this preſent I will ſay, that we Engliſh Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes are doubtleſſe moſt miſerable, who dayly enduring ſo many diſcommodities of this life for the Catholike faith, which wee profeſſe, and hauing prouoked <hi>his Maieſty,</hi> a Prince otherwiſe moſt merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, who profeſſeth the contrary Religion, to take diſpleaſure againſt vs, which of all the reſt wee account moſt greeuous, and hauing therefore for a long time beene, and are dayly made a pittifull ſpectacle to
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:19699:29"/>
this whole Kingdome; now by humble petition crauing to be inſtructed by <hi>your Holineſſe</hi> in thoſe things, which you by <hi>your Apoſtolical Breues</hi> haue to our moſt great temporall preiudice declared to be cleerely repugnant to the Catholike faith, doe not onely not deſerue ſo much at your hands, as to bee heard herein, but <hi>your Holineſſe</hi> alſo doth forbid and condemne our petition, and doth threaten the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour to be puniſhed with Cenſures, and other Eccleſiaſticall puniſhments, vnleſſe he purge himſelfe very ſpeedily, &amp; yet af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter an vnuſuall maner impeacheth him of no crime, whereof hee ſhould purge him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</p>
            <p n="16">16. For behold <hi>(moſt bleſſed Father)</hi> how miſerable, and to bee pittied is our caſe. <hi>Our Kings moſt excellent Maieſty,</hi> to whom by the law of Chriſt wee owe tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall obedience, doth demaund of vs, vnder paine of incurring moſt greeuous penalties, an Oath which hee affirmeth to bee onely a temporall Oath, and of Allea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance: <hi>your Holineſſe,</hi> to whom by the law alſo of Chriſt we are bound to obey in ſpirituals hath by <hi>your Breues</hi> altogether
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:19699:29"/>
condemned the ſame, as containing in it many things flat contrary to faith and ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, and hath withall declared, that all thoſe Prieſts, who either doe take the ſaid Oath, or doe teach, or ſhall teach that it may lawfully bee taken, ſhall bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priued of their faculties: <hi>Wee Engliſh Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes</hi> being betweene theſe two nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row ſtreights, and fearing leaſt that by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyding the gulfe of <hi>Charybdis,</hi> we ſhould fall vppon the rocke of <hi>Scylla,</hi> that is leaſt that wee ſhould not render to <hi>God</hi> or <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar,</hi> that which is their due, doe moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly requeſt <hi>your Holineſſe,</hi> who is our Supreme Paſtour in ſpiritualls, and whoſe proper office is to inſtruct &amp; confirme the ſheep of Chriſt in the Chriſtian faith, that you will bee pleaſed to ſhew vnto vs thoſe many things, or at leaſt-wiſe one among thoſe many, which in this Oath are ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant to faith and ſaluation, to the end that wee may both ſatisfie our owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, and alſo fulfill <hi>your Holineſſe</hi> and <hi>his Maiesties</hi> command, as much as in vs lyeth, and Catholike Religion will per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit: And neuertheleſſe <hi>your Holineſſe</hi> doth not onely not admitte our petition,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:19699:30"/>
wherein with all dutifull ſubmiſſion wee doe propound the reaſons and arguments, which are vſually obiected, againſt, and for the taking of the Oath, to bee exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by <hi>your Holineſſe,</hi> and affirming no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of our owne opinion; but you doe alſo by the euill information of others, as wee thinke, wholely condemne the ſame, without alleadging any crime either in perticular, or in generall againſt it, and doe declare, that the Authour thereof, or your humble petitioner, except hee purge himſelfe forthwith, ſhall bee greeuouſly puniſhed, and neuertheleſſe you make no mention of any crime at all, whereof hee ſhould purge himſelfe.</p>
            <p n="17">17 Is it perchance a crime for thoſe that are in ignorance, errour, and doubt, to haue recourſe to the Supreme Paſtour, and Doctor of the Church to be inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by him in faith, and to propound with due ſubmiſſion the doubts, and diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties, which trouble both their owne, and other mens conſciences, to bee an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſweared and ſatisfied by him, and that not in things of ſmall moment, but in ſuch as, vnder paine of incurring great penalties,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:19699:30"/>
do belong to they eelding of due obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Caeſar?</hi> Is it a crime for childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that are hungry, to craue bread of their Father, for ſheepe that want Paſture, to require foode of their Shepheard, for Diſciples that are ignorant, to beſeech humbly inſtruction of their Maiſter and Teacher? Wee Engliſh Catholikes doe acknowledge <hi>your Holineſſe</hi> to bee our ſpirituall Father, Paſtour, and Maiſter, and doe moſt humbly requeſt to bee inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by <hi>your Holineſſe</hi> in the Catholike faith, and in thoſe many things, which <hi>your Holineſſe</hi> by <hi>your Breues</hi> hath decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to be cleerely repugnant to faith and ſaluation: and <hi>your Holineſſe</hi> doth damne and forbid our petition, and doth or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine, after a maner altogether vnuſuall, that I the Authour thereof, who in the name of the reſt haue written, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed the ſame, except I purge my ſelfe very ſpeedily, ſhall bee puniſhed moſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerely: For, as I thinke in no tribunall on the earth, this cuſtome is to be found, that any man is compelled by ſentence of the iudge to purge himſelfe vnder paine of incurring moſt greeuous puniſhments,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:19699:31"/>
vnleſſe the Iudge doe make knowne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him the crime, for which if hee doe not purge himſelfe, hee is to be condemned: Beſides that it is impoſſible for one to purge himſelfe of that crime, whereof he is ignorant.</p>
            <p n="18">18 And to ſpeake freely the truth (for now I, being ſummoned before the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt tribunall on earth to purge my ſelfe, am by the law it ſelfe permitted to ſpeak ſomewhat more freely, ſo that I ſpeake truely and modeſtly) this new kinde of condemning the books of Catholike Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thours, and of commanding the Authour to purge himſelfe, being made by ſuch a publike Decree, and vnder paine of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curring the penalties contained in the <hi>Councell</hi> of <hi>Trent,</hi> and in the <hi>Index</hi> of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden bookes, without naming any crime either in particular, or in generall, for which they are condemned, and of which the Author ſhould purge himſelfe (conſidering that the ſame puniſhment is not appointed in the <hi>Index</hi> for reading, without diſtinction, all ſorts of forbidden bookes, neither doe all crimes require the ſame purgation) doth make both the <hi>See
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:19699:31"/>
Apoſtolike</hi> odious to the Aduerſaries of Catholike Religion, who will eaſily from hence take occaſion to perſwade them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, that the Biſhops of Rome are wont to reiect at their pleaſure, and to ſuppreſſe violently by threatnings, and not by ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments thoſe opinions which they doe not like, and to promote by fauours, not by reaſons, thoſe opinions, which are pleaſing vnto them; and alſo doth little ſatisfie prudent Catholikes, who can hardly perſwade themſelues, that the <hi>ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Congregation</hi> of the right <hi>Honorable Cardinals,</hi> who are deputed for the exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of bookes, (to whoſe informati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons <hi>your Holineſſe</hi> giuing credit, as we vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly doe imagine, hath condemned thoſe bookes, and ordained that the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor ſhall be ſeuerely puniſhed, vnleſſe he forthwith purge himſelfe) if they could haue found in them any propoſition, which is certainely knowne to bee here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall, erroneous, or repugnant to ſound doctrine, they would haue paſſed it ouer with ſo great ſilence, and (contrarie to to the vſuall manner of the See Apoſtolike in condemning the bookes of Catholike
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:19699:32"/>
Authors, but of ſuch eſpecially, who are commanded to purge themſelues, as by innumerable examples, which are extant in the tomes of the Councels, and in the Buls of Popes I could demonſtrate) com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand the Author to purge himſelfe one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in generall words, vvithout ſhewing him any crime either in particular, or in generall, of which hee ſhould purge him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</p>
            <p n="19">19 I therefore the <hi>Authour</hi> of thoſe bookes, whom the <hi>Sacred Congregation</hi> by the commandement of <hi>your Holineſſe</hi> hath enioyned to purge my ſelfe, but as yet I know not of what crime, a moſt du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull child of the Catholike Romane Church, and of <hi>your Holineſſe</hi> in ſpirituals, and withall a moſt faithfull Subiect of the Kingdome of England, and of our <hi>Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Lord King</hi> IAMES in temporals, being ſummoned before <hi>your Holineſſe</hi> his ſupreme tribunall to purge my ſelfe, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate at <hi>your Holineſſe</hi> feete, doe humbly requeſt you by the dreadfull <hi>Maieſtie</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> the <hi>Supreme Iudge</hi> of all: <hi>Firſt,</hi> that <hi>your Holineſſe</hi> will iudge that which is right, and doe mee iuſtice, and not giue
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:19699:32"/>
credit onely to the informations of them, who are my Aduerſaries in this contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſie, and haue foulely corrupted my words, contrarie to my meaning, but that you will examine my cauſe by your owne certaine knowledge, and that you vvill make knowne vnto mee all thoſe things, or at the leaſt wiſe ſome of them, which in thoſe bookes condemned by <hi>your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs</hi> commandement are cleerely known to bee repugnant to faith, or good man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners. For I proteſt, that I am moſt readie to correct thoſe things, which are to be corrected, to purge what is to be purged, to make more plaine what is to bee ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained, and to recall what is to bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>called.</p>
            <p n="20">20 <hi>Secondly,</hi> that if <hi>your Holineſſe,</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter due examination of my writings ſhall find, that you haue been miſ-informed by ſome perſons, and that nothing is to bee found in thoſe bookes, which is repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to Catholike Doctrine, as ſome per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance haue ſuggeſted to <hi>your Holineſſe,</hi> you will be pleaſed to recall that ſentence of the <hi>Sacred Congregation</hi> publiſhed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt mee and my bookes, through euill
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:19699:33"/>
information, or vehement importunitie of ſome men, or through miſvnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the true meaning of my words, and that you will haue a care of my good name, in that good ſort, as ſhall ſeeme fitting to your wiſedome, charitie, and iuſtice, and that you will account mee to bee a Catholike and a Childe of the Catholike Romane Church. For that which I did vvrite in another place,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Diſput. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Admonit. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> I doe here repeate againe. <hi>I am a Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like and a child of the Catholike Romane Church, and if any man, of what degree ſo euer hee be, ſhall wrongfully accuſe mee of hereſie, let him know aſſuredly, that by the aſſiſtance of Almightie God, I will by all thoſe meanes, which God and nature hath granted to innocent men to defend themſelues, to the vttermoſt of my power defend my ſelfe from their falſe accuſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, vntill the Church, beeing fully infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of my opinion, ſhall in plaine, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular words (for no man can recall errors, vntill he know particularly what they be) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne the ſame.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="21">21 <hi>Thirdly,</hi> that <hi>your Holineſſe,</hi> will command, that this my purgation, and
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:19699:33"/>
moſt humble petition may for future me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie be regiſtred among the Acts of the holy Office of the Inquiſition, as the condemnation of my bookes is recorded, as appeareth by the Decree it ſelfe, that thoſe, who hereafter ſhall ſucceede in that Office, may giue their ſentence and iudgement as well of this my purgation, as of that condemnation of my bookes, and whether I am to bee accounted a Catholike, and a child of the Church, or an heretike.</p>
            <p n="22">22 But if <hi>your Holineſse</hi> will not bee pleaſed to admit this my Purgation, and moſt humble Supplication, and to recall the ſentence denounced vpon euill infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation againſt my Bookes, and to haue a care of my good name, which hath wrongfully beene taken away, although I know right well, that the ſame mercifull and great God, who in times paſt preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the credit of <hi>Robert Groſseteſte</hi> By<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Lincolne, with whom <hi>Pope Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent</hi> the fourth being <hi>wonderfully offended,</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Mathew Paris ad an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num <hi>1253.</hi> §. diebus ſub eiſdem &amp; ad annum <hi>1254.</hi> §. Hoc etiam anno Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus Papa.</note> 
               <hi>determined to caſt his dead bones out of the Church, and to bring him into ſo great oblo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quie, that he ſhould bee proclaimed through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:19699:34"/>
the whole world for an Heathen, Rebell, and diſobedient, for that hee had written to the ſaid</hi> Pope Innocent <hi>in the ſpirit of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie and loue, that hee would correct his frequent or accuſtomed</hi>
               <note place="margin">Crebros <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>os errores <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orrigeret.</note> 
               <hi>errors,</hi> although I know, I ſay, that the ſame God, who is not an accepter of perſons, is able alſo to deliuer me from the vniuſt attempts, and falſe informations of any whatſoeuer, and to make knowne my innocency to <hi>your Holineſse,</hi> and to the whole Chriſtian World: neuertheleſſe prayers, teares, and patience, ioyned with the teſtimony of a good conſcience, ſhall be my cheefeſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge, and this ſhall bee my daily comfort, that it is no whit leſſe, but rather more happy and gratefull to God, to ſuffer per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution for Iuſtice ſake at the handes of Kinſmen, and of the ſame Houſhold, who in friendſhip and ſocietie ought to bee more ſtreightlie linked, then of Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers.</p>
            <p n="23">23 <hi>Finally,</hi> if in this my purgation, which the <hi>Sacred Congregation</hi> by commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>your Holineſse</hi> hath enioyned me, I haue offended any man, as I hope I haue not, by ſpeaking any thing not with that
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:19699:34"/>
circumſpection as is fitting, (for wittingly and willingly I would giue no man any iuſt cauſe of offence) I doe moſt humbly craue pardon both of <hi>your Holineſse,</hi> for whoſe temporall and perpetuall felicitie, I will continually pray vnto our moſt merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full God, and alſo of the whole Chriſtian world. From my Study in the <hi>Feaſt of S. Iohn Baptiſt.</hi> 1614.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>A moſt humble Childe, and Seruant of</hi> your Holineſſe, <hi>and of the</hi> Holy See Apoſtolike,</signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>The Authour of the Bookes as aforeſaid, &amp;c.</p>
            </postscript>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>Page 23. line 24. put out <hi>ſelfe.</hi> Page 45. line 7. <hi>them.</hi> Pag. 54. l. 2. writings. pag. 59. l. 1. yeelding. pag. 59. l. 18. manner.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
